U.S. Emergency Board No. 135 Records 5056
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Transcripts and Carrier Exhibits (Box 1)
  - Comparison of Board of Adjustment Provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association proposal dated April 15, 1960, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Comparison of sick leave provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    Compared with Flight Engineers International Association proposal as contained in Union Exhibit Number 6, Page 31, and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of physical examinations provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1960, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Comparison of missing, internment, prisoner of war, or hostage provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Comparison of group life insurance provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Estimated annual cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal that employee group insurance plan be made non-contributory (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Comparison of employer and employee contributions-pension provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Comparison of employer and employee contributions provisions of Pan American Airways flight engineer pension plan, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 104)
    Compared with Flight Engineers International Association proposal dated April 15, 1960 and similar provisions of other airline pension plans governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Estimated annual cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 105)
    Proposal that the cooperative retirement income trust plan for flight engineers be amended to make it non-contributory (based on experience for the calendar year 1960)
  - Estimated annual cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 106)
    Proposal that the cooperative retirement income trust plan for flight engineers be amended to make it non-contributory (based on experience for the calendar year of 1960 increased for proposed rates)
  - Examples of Pan American World Airways, Incorporated collective bargaining agreements (Box 1, Folder 107)
    Agreements in which the Pay Provision became effective after the reopening date of the preceding agreement
  - Excerpt from Report to the President by Emergency Board Number 93 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Comparison of duration provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 109)
    Compared with similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of dual assignment pay provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Comparison of vacation entitlement provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Comparison of deadheading provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Analysis of cost potential of Flight Engineers International Association proposed article 8 (c) furlough pay (Box 1, Folder 113)
    Compared with interim agreement and present agreement
  - Analysis of Flight Engineers International Association Exhibit Number 67: index of hourly rate of selected clerical workers, 1945-1960 (Box 1, Folder 114)
    Compared with Index of Earnings of Pan American Airways flight engineers 1945-1960
  - Index of hourly rate or senior stock clerk compared with index of monthly earnings of flight engineers (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Analysis of Flight Engineers International Association Exhibit Number 66 "Hourly Wage Rates of Service Supply Clerk" (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Going industry stock clerk and senior stock clerk rates at time of Pan American Airways contract reopening (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Analysis of increased annual cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposed pay rates based on status and equipment distribution at 80 hours, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 118)
    As of April 15, 1961
  - Summary of estimated increased annual cost impact of Flight Engineer International Association proposals (Box 1, Folder 119)
- Union Exhibits (Box 2)
  - Envelope (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Number of flight engineers involved in Pan American Airways, Incorporated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Civil Aircraft operated by Pan American Airways, Incorporated as of December 31, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - History and business of Pan American World Airways, Incorporated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - History of dispute between Pan American World Airways, Incorporated and Pan American Airways Chapter, Flight Engineers International Association (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Comparison of existing provisions in contract between Pan American World Airways, Incorporated and Pan American Airways Chapter, Flight Engineers International Association, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Compared with changed proposed by the parties
  - Performance supplement (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Maintenance log (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Official log (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Crew layover policy guide (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pan American World Airways Atlantic Division Manual 20.04.06 Flight Crew Layover Accommodations (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Federal Aviation Agency regulations on recurrent training (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cities served by Pan American World Airways, Incorporated and code designations (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Departure report time (letter) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Comparison of flight time, duty time, and elapsed time in piston and jet operations Idlewild to Paris, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Comparison of flight time, duty time, and elapsed time in piston and jet operations Idlewild to Dusseldorph, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Comparison of flight time, duty time, and elapsed time in piston and jet operations San Francisco to Sydney and return, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Comparison of flight time, duty time and elapsed time in piston and jet operations Idlewild to Nassau and return, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Comparison of flight time, duty time, and elapsed time in piston and jet aircraft operations Idlewild to San Juan and return, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - An example of scheduling time versus actual time (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Examples of "Long Duty Days" for flight engineers of Pan American World Airways, Incorporated, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Scheduled long duty single flight engineer crew patterns in Overseas Division, Atlantic Area, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    April, 1961
  - Memorandum regarding vacancies B-707 type aircraft (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Selected characteristics of different types of planes (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Mileage and total hourly rates for pilots and flight engineers of Pan American Airways, Incorporated for Dc-8 planes, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Pay yields for pilots and flight engineers on specified planes Pan American Airways, Incorporated, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Engineer seniority list, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    January 1, 1961
  - Flight engineer base station vacancy bulleting number 61/2 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Memorandum of agreement (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Transfer and travel expenses (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Provision for release time before and after transfer in agreement between Pan American World Airways, Incorporated and the pilots (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Decision Number 83 of the National Labor Board in the matter of the air line pilots' wage dispute (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Excerpts from the Civil Air Regulations, Part 41 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Excerpts from Emergency Board Report in cases between Trans World Airlines, et. Al., and Air Line Pilots Association, International (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Effect of heavier and faster planes on employment (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Schedule of potential mileage at pegged speeds (Pan American Aircraft) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Flying time on selected non-stop jet service trips via Pan American World Airways, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    March, 1961
  - Comparison of selected rations in piston and jet operations Idlewild to Paris and return, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Exhibit 38, 38A
  - Comparison of selected ratios in piston and jet operations Idlewild to Dusseldorf and return, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Exhibits 39, 39A
  - Comparison of selected ratios in piston and jet operations San Francisco to Sydney and Return, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Exhibits 40, 40A
  - Flight time and ground time comparison based on equipment schedule - Latin American Division, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    March 1958 and March 1961
  - Comparison of selected ratios in piston and jet operations by trips, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Exhibits 42, 42A
  - Excerpt from the Adamson Eight-Hour Act ordering an eight-hour work day for railway operating employees, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Approved on September 3, 5, 1916
  - Average number of miles per hour for engineers and firemen in passenger service of Class I railroads, 1922-1959 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Average hours actually worked per employee per week: engineers and firemen in passenger service of Class I railroads, 1922-1959 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Proposals of railroad operating employees for changes in rules relating to hours of service, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - The forty-hour week on American railroads excerpt from the Emergency Board Report on Wages and Hours for Non-Operating Railway Employees, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    December 17, 1948
  - Forty-hour week agreement regarding non-operating railroad employees of Class I railroads, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    March 19, 1949
  - Excerpt from report of Senate Committee on labor and public welfare in dispute between the railway carriers and four operating brotherhoods (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Excerpt from Report to the President by Emergency Board Number 110 (National Mediation Board Case Number A-4854), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    July 30, 1955
  - Reduction of workweek for maritime employees (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Typical wage rates and increases, maritime employees under approved wage and hour agreement (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Excerpt from Report to the President by the Emergency Board regarding Northwest Airlines, Incorporated and the International Association of Machinists, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    August 7, 1946
  - Present monthly yields for Pan American flight engineers on specified aircraft compared with yields proposed by the union (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - History of flight engineers' rates at Pan American Airways, Incorporated, 1945-1957 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - National Progress in Productivity and Living Standards (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Employee productivity of air carrier operations total scheduled service, 1947-1959 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Productivity of Pan American Airways Employees, 1947-1959 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Flight engineers' monthly earnings requested to incorporate normal improvement in living standards - Pan American Airways, Incorporated, 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Change in engine wage brackets in passenger service, 1922-1960 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Change in engine wage brackets in passenger service, 1922-1960 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Progress of basic daily rates, road passenger engineers, 1922-1961 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    1922-March 1961
  - General wage increase of road operating and non-operating railway. Employees of Class I Line-Haul Railways, 1946-1961 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Increase in straight-time hourly earnings of production workers in United States Manufacturing Industries since June 1957 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Increase in straight-time hourly earnings of all employees and of non-operating employees and of basic daily rates of passenger engineers on Class I Line-Haul Railways since June 1957 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Hourly wage rates of service supply clerks - Pan-American Airways, Incorporated, 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Index of hourly rate of selected clerical workers compared with index of monthly earnings of flight engineers - Pan American Airways, Incorporated, 1945- 1960 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Components in pay formula for pilots - Pan American World Airways, Incorporated, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    1957 and 1959
  - Yields for first pilots of Pan American World Airways, Incorporated, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Computation of time (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Provisions for computation of flight time - airline agreement covering flight engineers (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Duty time guarantee agreement between Pan American World Airways and Air Line Pilots, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Operational duty pay for flight engineers - Trans World Airlines, Incorporated, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Interim agreement between Eastern Air Lines, Incorporated and the Flight Engineers in the Service of Eastern Air Lines, Incorporated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    As represented by the Flight Engineers International Association
  - Severance Pay, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Benefits in major layoff plans (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Excerpt from memorandum of agreement on mechanization and modernization between Pacific Maritime Association and Longshoremen and Warehousemen, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    October 18, 1960
  - Provisions governing daily and monthly rest periods in airline agreements covering flight engineers (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Excerpt from Slick Airways, Incorporated and the Flight Engineers in the Service of Slick Airways, Incorporated. Agreement. (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Related wage practices covering moving expenses for federal government employees since 1924 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Memorandum regarding land flight crew sick leave plan (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Comparison of provisions for physical examinations for pilots - Pan American World Airways, Incorporated, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    Compared with provisions requested by the Flight Engineers
  - Copies of agreement to be furnished to flight engineers - provisions in airline's contracts (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Group Life Insurance for Active Employees of Pan American Airways, Incorporated (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Excerpt from Steel Memorandum of Agreement, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Basic Patterns in Pensions, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Improvement in retirement plans in Union Agreements, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Seniority list furnished to each flight engineer - provisions in airline Agreements covering flight engineers (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Contract expiration of reopening dates - Major Airlines (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Flight Engineers International Association-Trans World Airlines Interim Proposal (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Appendix A Pan American-Teamsters Agreement, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    Effective February 1, 1959-March 3, 1961. Signed March 27, 1959.
  - Excerpts from Report to the President by the Emergency Board Number 122 appointed by Executive Order 10757, pursuant to Section 10 of the Railway Labor Act, as amended, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    Dated February 27, 1959
  - Indices of scheduled flights and numbers of passengers carried by Pan American World Airways, Incorporated, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Operating expenses per employee have increased at a faster rate than operating revenues per employee, resulting in a steadily worsening position, 1956- 1960 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Pan American says its traffic in April rose 10 percent from 1960 month, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Estimated aggregate hours and miles to be flown by additional flight engineer officers allegedly required to meet Flight Engineers International Association Proposals (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Effect of Variation in Method of Calculation of Company Cost Estimates, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    Exhibit 97A: Analysis of increased annual cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association based on status and equipment distribution. April 15, 1961.
  - DC-8 Flight Engineers Officer's Chart (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Increased productivity per flight engineer pay hour - Pan American World Airways, Incorporated, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Fluctuations in the rate of productivity increase (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Increase in monthly earnings of flight engineers compared with increase in consumer price index, 1946-1957 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Comparison of 80-hour flight engineer officer maximum yield for L-049 under 1953 and 1955 agreements inflated for consumer price index change and by various productivity improvement factors, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    Compared to 80-hour Flight Engineer Officer maximum yield under next negotiated agreements
  - Adjustments to offset reductions in hours are not basic wage increases (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Maintenance of weekly wages (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Comparison of Pan American Airways Assistant Engineer Officer Pay at 70, 75, 80, and 85 hours (Box 2, Folder 105)
    Compared with pay of flight engineers of other carriers employing non-pilot engineers at seventh six month period of service
  - Index of hourly rate of selected clerical workers compared with index of earnings of Pan American Airways flight engineers (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Index of hourly rate of sales personnel compared with index of earnings of Pan American Airways flight engineers (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Earnings of a flight engineer on a DC-6B by selected airlines at time of Pan American Airways 1957 settlement (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Comparison of pay yields for flight engineers in international service, Northwest Airlines, Incorporated and Pan American Airlines, Incorporated, 1945-1958 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Comparison of pay yields for flight engineers in international service, Trans World Airlines, Incorporated, and Pan American Airlines, Incorporated (Box 2, Folder 110)